collective insights as a voyage through
topics and technology is revolutionizing
human wellbeing groundbreaking
approaches for a better world and a
better life away you welcome a
collective insights very first episode
of the neural hacker collective podcast
we wanted to start a podcast where we
can have these video dialogues because
we have such interesting and brilliant
people in our network who have various
expertise in areas of neuroscience
cognitive enhancement psychological
development etc so this is the first of
these dialogues my name is daniel
shramko Berger I'm heading up research
and development here and this is my
first time to be on this side of a
podcast so forgive my clumsiness with it
and we are very excited to have the
first conversation be with dr. Zachary
Stein Zak is a very good friend and
really brilliant and innovative thinker
he is a philosopher of Education the
background and meta theory integral
theory developmental psychology
psychometrics
did his work in education and
psychometrics at Harvard with Howard
Gardner and that whole multiple lines of
intelligence advancing what we think of
as intelligence world work with Kirk
Fischer on advanced developmental
psychology and in the integral
philosophy on that and has written books
on the topic which we might get into a
bit and our topic today is understanding
what intelligence is what IQ is and EQ
and other kind of metrics related to
intelligence where they're good where
they're not adequate what we're actually
talking about when we talk about
intelligence what's actually meaningful
here what are better ways of defining it
and assessing it and then how much of it
is fixed how much is changeable and what
are the what do we know about how to
actually advance and develop what is
actually worth developing here so this
is a topic that I don't know anyone who
knows more about that the depth of the
philosophy Upton Zack Zack amongst other
things was a founder of a really
fascinating organization
Electrical co-founder there which is a
method for advanced psychometric
development across lots of lines looking
at someone's development in different
aspects of cognition their development
and ethics and their epistemology and
their moral reasoning and how do we
assess those things how does the
assessment affect the nature of what
we're assessing all like that so Zach
thank you for being here today with us
I'm so excited Daniel there's like no
conversation I'd rather be so
intelligence let's just dive right in I
think there are probably no scores that
people have identified with as being
important metrics of their capacity than
IQ maybe so I'm curious for you to just
start with the education of us how did
the IQ development how did that score
come about what does it actually measure
how does that relate to the total
picture of what intelligence is what are
multiple lines of intelligence and how
should we think about intelligence I
think everyone has a kind of intuitive
sense of something that relates to
processing speed and memory and
computational power that is kind of in
distinction to artistic inclination or
interpersonal inclination so start us
off dive in how should we think about
intelligence what are the problems that
we think about it yeah
so it's interesting you start with the
notion of score is that's really one of
the hearts of the issues here is that we
have connected intelligence which is
something that goes on in the mind with
a particular instrument right that's
been used to detect intelligence
so-called err supposedly detect
intelligence for a very long time and so
I think one of the things we need to
think about the IQ test and
disentangling that a little bit from our
conceptions of intelligence because
we've ratified and simplified and I
think drastically oversimplified and
there's many great histories of IQ
testing I really like Stephen Jay Gould
great work called the MIS measure of man
and you see from reading this book that
the IQ test was
not an instrument of science but an
instrument of bureaucracy and had to do
with the quantitative excuse me the
socio political history of quantitative
objectivity I said this has to do with
the use of numbers in the manipulation
of people and this is a very important
aspect of modernity and it was hugely
liberating and things like public health
and sense is taking in other areas where
mathematics liberated us into this new
realm of social engineering but of
course every step forward as a as a
dialectic to these kinds of developments
and so what you find with the IQ test is
that in France turn a century you know
late 18-hundreds Binet was tasked by the
French government to create a test that
could be used to basically keep certain
types of kids out of schools and given a
special attention so Binet was someone
who specialized in a whole bunch of
psychological fields but especially the
rehabilitation of the learning disabled
so the IQ test was really just a very
gross sorting mechanism created in
France to find those kids who needed
special attention and Binet was very
explicit and Stephen Jay Gould gives us
beautiful account of Benes dismay and
concern at the reification of IQ he
thought this was just an instrument just
to use to sort kids in a useful way in
the public interest it's not in any way
a theory by the nature of the mind or
about the nature of intelligence that
whole idea that the IQ test measures
this intelligent kind of general
intelligence which is then genetically
transmitted not all idea came from the
Americans who imported the IQ test at
the beginning of the First World War and
at the same time traded the
multiple-choice test and move we got
kind of large-scale industrial-strength
standardized testing and that's a gift
of the kind of world war one kind of
scramble the preamble to World War one
scramble in America
so what was first just an instrument
used to sort children to give them
special attention with no psychological
theory accompanied right get that it was
a theoretical became an instrument that
was standardized that was used to sort
adults and children and that came loaded
with theoretical baggage about a general
intelligence and about its genetic
heritability and so there's a long leg
of legacy which of course Google lays
out of how this got tightened the
eugenics movement I'm not going to get
into that because I think it's a
distraction the key that I want to point
out here is that IQ as we think about it
right and saturated the culture but it's
not as theorized as it needs to be right
it's a my call it a mongrel concept
right which is to say it's a concept
that kind of supervenes on the actual
realities of the mind right it's
touching some things it's a it's what
Roy Bhaskar the great meta theorist the
great philosopher you know the late
great he called it a demi reality which
is to say as minions it's like it's
getting at something real but it's a
small version of what's real this is the
IQ so I like to compare to the GDP as a
number right the gross domestic product
massively complex national economy but
again in the scramble of a war effort
just synthesized and to organize give it
one number and put it on the linear
trajectory and use it to rank countries
unilaterally and they get a single most
valuable thing easy thing to do with it
with a number but a clear
oversimplification and so likewise you
know it's not that you're not getting at
something you're getting at something
right but it's a demi reality it's a
small round so the IQ test became this
and a truncated our thinking about the
nature of intelligence and it became
hypertrophy and a lot of people don't
realize that the IQ test was then
created up and complicated a little bit
taken by the Educational Testing Service
and made into the the SAT and so there's
this long kind of continuous history of
the use of these forms of quote
intelligence testing not really for
scientific research about intelligence
for the organization of educational
systems and large-scale bureaucracies
like the army which was where the first
large-scale standardized test was ever
created it was for the army alpha 1 and
alpha 2 which were to sort the incoming
millions into the American army for the
world war 1 so that's kind of the brief
history of where this instrument came
from and so I'm not a big fan of the
instrument itself now there's been
improvements to it we have these new
fangled lungs that raven matrices and
some problems have been solved with
objectivity and reliability which were
the first big concerns so I'm going to
kind of skip that side piece but I want
to talk about is the way that we've got
we're kind of addicted to a simplistic
way of thinking about intelligence right
and actually many people have an allergy
to thinking about it in a more complex
way and you know Howard Gardner and Curt
Fisher who I studied with at Harvard all
they wanted to do was talk about it in a
more complex way and they had very
little interest in anything like general
intelligence and thought it was actually
a concept that was dangerous right
Howard Gardner once said to me know that
intelligence is the most political of
all the psychological concepts right
because it becomes the meritocracies
kind of yardstick and so yeah so that's
a little bit of a preamble to like okay
let's deliberate thinking about
intelligence from the idea and start
intelligence in a more complex way when
you say that the concept has been very
reified obviously it has right even
though it started out without a really
clear philosophical foundation but let's
take groups like Mensa right let's take
the way it's been used in military or
any other kind of institution not just
for rooting out who is not qualified but
also who is qualified for higher level
capacities you would think that if it
didn't map in some way to reality the
concept wouldn't have withstood this
much time so what is it measuring and
how does that correlate to reality and
then also what is it not measuring I
would love to go in there a little bit
yeah absolutely and like I said it is
measuring something just like just like
GDP is measuring something so it's not
that it's
out of touch with reality it's at its
revealing unreality in a way that's not
revealing as much as we could so it's
drastically oversimplifying it's kind of
like taking a complex ecosystem and
giving it a single number when in fact
there are many things happening in the
ecosystem which could be given different
numbers and so in some institutional
context that's very valuable and first
when you're for example starting a huge
army from scratch with a bunch of
American farm boys anyone to figure out
like who could potentially be in general
like it's very useful than a gross way
to sort that and so this is important
but when you start thinking about what
what then what does it measure yeah to
being in general well right and that's
what I'm saying I'm not sure this is a
question then we have to go deeper and
think well then what's the nature of the
mind because what does it measure means
well what's there to measure you know
and so that's where we need to tell a
story about cognitive development and
about the nature of the mind and how it
grows and what the nature of learning is
and what the nature of what we call
intelligence actually is busting the dam
in reality to get to the actual reality
of intelligence so my favorite phrase of
Piaget is the idea that intelligence is
the grasp of consciousness right which
is to say its intelligence is
consciousness operating world right and
so when we look at what intelligence is
what it has to do is it's these kind of
skillful manipulation or operation first
on the physical been on representations
and on abstraction then on principles
and actions right which is to say that
it's one thing to move physical objects
around in a skillful way which humans
have done since who knows how long
millions of years all right but now
we're moving around principles and
axioms of science in the skillful way so
we're looking at a spectrum of cognitive
complexity that grows over time and you
know the Piaget that was kind of
chastised in your introduction in the
psychology course that is not the actual
Piaget
and kurt fischer i think is probably one
of the most important psychologists of
the 20th century in part because he kept
the puget and vision of this
hierarchical cognitive architecture that
emerges over time so what we look at IQ
is in many ways a generalized if you
want to go their capacity for building
skills of this hierarchy right now what
we're missing with a typical way of kind
of capturing some of those skills and
saying those are valuable those are
intelligence is that there's a very wide
array of skills like huge number of
skills that you can build and only some
of those Mac with what we measure on IQ
so there are many people who are
radically skilled at building really
quickly skills up this hierarchy of
skill they're just not this kind of
stuff that we measure and value on IQ
tests so that's kind of in one of the
ways to slice this pie is to say that
multiple lines of intelligence model
crucifies say multiple lines of
intelligence and so if there's anything
like a generalized intelligence it has
to do with your basic capacity to build
in any intelligence right and so some
people are gifted at building in
mathematical intelligences which is to
say they can move up and down this
hierarchy of complexity think an
abstraction they can do that in math
really well that's measured on IQ tests
right other people can move up and down
this abstraction and complexity and
let's say music or dance right and there
are hierarchies of abstraction and dance
if you've seen a skilled dancer that you
have is someone who's supervening on a
lot of possible moves and building this
trajectory towards an aesthetic
experience that's a very abstract thing
to do very complex skill development
you're not gonna get that an IQ test
also not valued in the army you know in
the places where IQ tests find the
people who do the work right and the
predictive validity I think is sketchy
too so I think one of the myths we need
to bust is that these people who do
great on IQ tests actually do great in
the world like this is we need to look
into that just like the SAT and the GRE
have very minimal predictive validity
there are studies that show the GRE to
be negatively predictive of graduate
school success
which is to say you do good on the GRE
you actually do bad at writing a
dissertation it's interesting right like
I did terrible on these kinds of tests
i'm dyslexic this is little personal i
did pretty good at writing a
dissertation and so i think there's this
complicated kind of cluster of things
that make us look at particular types of
skill development in particular
capacities from particular lines that's
what we value that's intelligence need
to think more broadly and in the kind of
context or in globally you know I think
it was Hunter s Thompson who said when
the going gets weird the weird turn pro
right and this is the situation we're in
and so we need to start looking at these
much different forms of intelligence but
still thinking about growing right and
so it becomes less about one form of
intelligence and more about many and the
functional fit and the unique profile of
the individual it's a worthwhile concept
amongst the multiple lines of
intelligence two separate ones that seem
more generally abstract form or embodied
so and this is just fitting a very rough
intuition I think many people have say
you take the mathematical line of
development and you take linguistic and
then maybe you take some orientation
towards the physical sciences right and
you cluster those things and you say
computers could get fairly good at that
without symbol rounding problem issues
right without sensorial grounding but
dance and maybe certain kinds of
interpersonal and naturalistic and maybe
even numinous or spiritual intelligences
kind of cluster differently maybe we say
they shouldn't we shouldn't cluster them
at all they're a totally different
things
but is there a clustering like that that
makes any sense and then it is there
something that we can think of as
general implicates within the more
cognitive domains that is accessible
yeah and it's a great question and this
was one of the questions that drove the
new OPI dance because the new Canadians
got to the point where they say okay we
know there are still these levels but
it's not like one big jump up yeah it's
many little jumps in many different
areas like a growing tree many branches
like the Darwinian metaphor but it's
skill development
but they said you know that like this
other intuitively there's clusters you
know if you're good at physics and math
it doesn't mean you're gonna be good at
dance you know but if you're good in
physics at math you probably will be
good at biology so there's the kind of
near and far transfer problem and that
lent to the issue of possible basic
structures underlying kind of deeper
branches in this trees of development
and so Robbie case who's doing another
great newbie yet in the University of
Toronto close Fisher colleague they did
some of the first dynamic systems
modeling of these things and they found
some of these deep structures it's
interesting mathematical psychology but
what they showed Robbie case in
particular was that there was something
like a deep structure to the
mathematical domain and it was the
number line and he had this incredibly
simple study where he showed if you
introduce inner-city kids to the number
line before any other mathematics which
by the way they don't get because they
don't have like calendars hanging on the
wall and their parents like I'm talking
them about Lanier's things and they're
not playing chutes and ladders like in a
calm environment stuff but you show them
this number line they're doing as well
and first grade as any of these kids
from the suburbs because they got the
basic structure of the mathematical
domain which was in the simplified
manner the number one so there are other
similar basic structures let's say with
perspective-taking that's social all
right so I probably case thought there
was probably one for a kind of
mathematics spatio-temporal
and there was probably long for
interpersonal and I think there's also
one for interpersonal which is to say
your relation to yourself so if I were
to cluster the lines ever cluster them
around the classic big three which would
be the I that we and the it and so I do
think typically what we think of it as
intelligence is really
facility with skill development in the
domain of objective mathematical
spatio-temporal realities the kind of
stuff that you push around in space and
time but there are other domains there's
a whole cluster of domains of socio
ethical which has to do abstraction for
a minute so please rubik's cube is
moving around spatio-temporal temporal
physical things but then as you move up
into actual axioms but axioms about say
physics right so you're you're now
to a degree of abstraction that requires
not relating with just sensorial reality
but that requires mapping to sense for a
reality in a different way than the
intra or interpersonal domains would so
precisely that Maps all the way up in
abstract that kind exactly so imagine
three brand that tree comes up three
branches go out each of those branches
go all the way up to the axioms and so
this the the spatio-temporal logical
mathematical one starts with the kids
learning gravity and the ball bouncing
and all of the things you do in the
spatio-temporal were the PJ investigated
he mostly investigated that line
investigated the emergence of things
like the idea of causality right there's
a time before kids understand causality
rate then they come to understand
cosmology cause and effect then you get
hypothetical deductive reasoning which
is still a higher more abstract in that
domain but whole of the things happen in
that other branch of the socio you know
moral and ethical and similarly with the
intra but they're all related as well
and the brain says inter tangle at the
higher levels so this is the view again
the IQ test what we think of is over
there sorry we look at the objective
branch right mathematics sciences etc
how well does IQ map to actual
proclivity there so say you have someone
that solve a Rubik's cubes very quickly
will they actually be more likely to
have novel developments in physics as a
scientist or might they just be great at
puzzles that are already defined but not
creative intelligence within that domain
I've heard some stories of like Niels
Bohr being a very slow thinker but
having a slow process that led to
profound originality so let's talk about
even within the realm of reasoning about
objective reality different kinds of
intelligence patterns yeah no and and
this is one of the big questions in
intelligence research even those who
transcended the IQ concept like Stern
Bergen and and Gardner there was
discretion of okay iq does seem to
predict something in some areas but
what's interesting Howard wrote a book
called creative minds and basically
this book is about this question and it
turns out that many scientists like
Einstein for example you know Einstein's
reading Spinoza and playing violin like
in a little philosophical reading group
as a patent clerk before relativity you
know I mean and then you look at other
scientists who have far transfer away
from the scientific domain typically to
some other area which then gives
inspiration back to the scientific
domain and this is you know one of the
things we're seeing collecting it too is
that you the broader your base right the
healthier any of those branch has become
and more easy the transfer is so you do
in a sense can predict in the simple way
this guy's gonna be able to do those
equations right he's got this simple
kind of kind of horsepower in the
cognitive kind of domain to do the
equations but is it going to be the
innovative guy who comes up with totally
new equations right or realize that
those equations aren't the equations we
should be doing so that's different than
intelligence right so creative problem
finding it's different than even
creative problem solving let alone
problem solving it's not creative that's
routine which requires a lot of
intelligence right which is a whole
class of problems that are very
difficult but routine and then there are
problems people don't even know yet and
so they again there's a space of
unexplored of higher human potentials
and forms of creativity but I think our
schooling hasn't allowed us to see what
happens when you take some of the super
high mathematical IQ and teach them to
meditate you just defined a number of
important concepts before we lose them
oh there's some cross training that you
mentioned which is important but
specifically you defined problem solving
and problem finding as fundamentally
different kinds of happens and it seems
seems to me like problem solving within
an already existing problem domain kind
of maps to hill climbing right and
problem finding maps to valley crossing
from a kind of evolutionary biology
perspective which Eric Weinstein says
the first one is what we call excellent
the second is remarkable remarkable
figures out new shit excellent does a
good job at predefined stuff so Rubik's
Cube is obviously problem solving right
figuring out new things that we
were in the unknown unknown requires a
different kind of exploration how do you
assess each of those differentially and
again the assessment question is this
tough I mean that's the million-dollar
question in a way literally because of
the political economy of the testing
industry but if you can find a way to
measure that creativity if you can you
know and the valley crossing hill
climbing metaphor is apt I think that's
the kind of thing we're talking about
here we're talking about those forms of
creativity that break into new realms
and you know I think I want to say about
assessing the honest answer is I don't
know how to assess it I think what we
know how to assess is well we know how
to assess which is people you know
working with how to know and as IQ
mapped more to Hill cross to hill
climbing than belly crossing definitely
definitely now I think the reason why
that's not true sometimes is because as
I said if you take someone who's got
that and throw in an extra spice of
something that they may not even be in
their environment because precisely
they're the high IQ guy who gets kept
away from those things right there that
he's the kayak you got who goes to just
do math and blahblah sends them to the
zendo you don't even get him doing yeah
yeah exactly and so so yeah so I think
that's one of the lessons here is that
the IQ tests can make can make it seem
like that's it when in fact that's the
kind of basic ingredients that let as it
were in one of the areas and you need to
bring more to it and that's just I think
part of the part of the picture
you know skill development the way a
Fisher thought about it had a very
intuitive way of thinking about growth
and not just static unchangeable
capacity but growth and emergence of new
capacity and that's the way the mind
works I think that's the other fallacy
of the IQ and the way intelligence is
often conceived is that it's either
you're smarter you're not smart
all right well in fact everything we
know about the mind is that it's
changing literally all the time first of
all
so you can be smart in the morning and
not smart than the late evening or vice
versa
but it's also changing over the course
of the lifespan drastically and I
already sketched a hierarchy from the
sensorimotor to the representational to
the abstract to the principal to the
axiomatic and that's a spectrum of
hierarchical complexity that takes
literally decades to unfold and the
right socio-cultural conditions a few
questions in Devon so when we think
about hyper specialization within a very
specific line and maybe even a specific
subset of the line versus some cross
training that leads to different kind of
generalize capacities so let's take like
let's take a Bucky fuller polymath type
or like a paul air dish almost savant
extreme specialist type right so you get
somebody like air dish and math who
develops graph theory in a way that
nobody else was even close but he
couldn't tie a shoe to really do
anything else functionally he had
obviously allocated like something had
happened but all the horsepowers
allocating weight but in a way that
created real novel value right then you
see other people where they have novel
value development across many fields
that are obviously inner informing each
other because of lateral thinking and
because of abstraction that is then
finding generalized principles across
domains what's the difference and what's
happening with those people and how much
of that is intrinsic versus developed
versus reinforced I think so hard to
tell and I mean the one lesson about the
mind is I think you need a uniqueness
you Nissa T which is to say that it's
you don't know you know it's the the
mind is a complex dynamical system and
so the butterfly can flap at one point
in childhood then you get a storm in
Chicago late in adulthood and you don't
know you can't connect those dots and so
it's interesting you know I think Kurt
Fisher again I keep bringing him up he's
my beloved you know advisor he always
tells a story these two theoretical
physicists they knew both hit by cars
crossing a street right which is to say
again you know Einstein the torso he was
you know he wouldn't cash his paycheck
he'd use it as like a slip in his book
it's a bookmark and then his secretary
if I didn't can put in this yeah he
would didn't so
there's a soul hypothesis you know when
you move up this hierarchy
representations abstractions principles
actions you know why would we need to do
that and that's the bana like what's a
million years ago like why is that a
capacity of the brain it's a strange
thing and so one thought is that as you
move up that you're kind of recycling
some of your neuronal material which is
to say that every move in growth is also
a loss like were and every time you grow
up right you also lose little so that's
one of the reasons child childhood is so
kind of bittersweet in and you have
these memories that are so interesting
because you know there was something as
a child that you no longer have that in
some ways was as valuable but it had to
be lost as you grew and that way of
thing about the mind is way more
attractive to me and then thinking about
well you were smart kid and I are
smarter don't lie yeah just that's one
but you're also this very complex
growing organism the minds like an
organism that literally metabolizes its
environment and depending on what it
metabolizes it grows in certain ways or
doesn't so what you're saying I mean it
obviously makes sense that no matter how
much muscular development we have the
moment we stop developing those muscles
they start to shrink if they require
continuous input that that could be the
same with cognitive or psycho-emotional
or other tasks but there's also a
zero-sum element what you're saying in
terms of total memory bandwidth and
complexity of processing where if we
develop in some areas it's almost like
there has to be neuro plastic
restructuring for optimization for those
kinds of things at the cost of
optimization for other things which of
course makes perfect sense and I think
is the way we usually think of it
there's a thought that's very
interesting to me which is a nonzero-sum
right deposited somewhere one can
develop new capacities well enforcing
existing capacities and just have more
net capacity more computational capacity
across the spectrum speak to me yeah
absolutely and this was often called
explicitly thematized far transfer right
and so what this is just a fancy way of
saying like no you let's say you're a
really smart guy mathematics and you
start to learn the piano you start to
learn the piano and you've never played
before but you have a PhD in something
here it'd have to be like a little kid
for many weeks
many months maybe years now that could
be very frustrating and you can separate
it from everything else you know I can't
try to build it as an independent skill
or you can find a way to interweave this
new skill development with your existing
high level skill and Fischer would often
talk about bringing a structure you know
transferring it over and down and then
you kind of get this helix model where
you're bringing in everything that
you're growing instead of growing things
out in the separate places and you see
this all the time so it's like you'll
have a meditation practice as you leave
somewhere when you go to work right or
you're you go to the gym and then you
come out and eat shit and so I think
there's this issue of the segmentation
and again there's all these
socio-cultural reasons for that so the
explicitly thematized fire transfer or
even near transferring is what you're
saying it's about bringing a kind of
coherence to the skill development so
you don't have this fractured weird
profile of skills but rather skills that
are coherently related to one another
you know it's gonna be hard to pull off
you know because we often have the
hypertrophy skills in certain areas rain
seems to me to be what is the mattock of
all of the polymaths
that we study is that they didn't they
didn't actually categorize your segments
the different areas in which they had
expertise is fundamentally different
they thought about Universal reality as
a much more integrated thing and what
they were studying in ecology became a
model for how they thought about
economics or psychology or biology right
so they would then go to an abstraction
level called complex systems right or
complex causation whatever and then they
would think about the lateral
application of principles one domain to
other domains so there there was of
course no just net memory because
everything actually made sense and
crossing in a referenced yeah it's a
learning modality I think it's schooling
is a big deal here we wouldn't have IQ
tests if we didn't have the factory
schools and we wouldn't think about the
nature of the disciplines the way we do
if we didn't have you know the kind of
post-war military industrial university
comics I mean it's very regimented if
you think about the training for example
of the highly specialized engineers and
doctors and these people
and so I'm very much a fan of you know
blurring some of these distinctions
doesn't doesn't even lessening expertise
but it means you know bringing more to
that and humanizing it always been the
call of the philosopher of Education is
to bring the humanities into the science
departments if only so they do better
science you know not so they don't do
science but so they do they can make the
creative like the Gaia hypothesis brings
in you know ancient Greek myth it's
that's profound when you see like The
DaVinci machine doing surgery better
than any surgeon right and that we're
entering a domain in which almost every
human skill that would require expertise
is becoming automatable better than we
do it but the process to build
automation technologies requires not
just hill climbing but valley crossing
kinds of intelligence to figure out what
those domains are and how to do them how
do you see the need for hyper
specialization changing with advanced
technology exponential tech and
automation
yeah I mean I think the people at the
edges of those fields don't even really
think about what the disciplinary
boundaries are or ought to be I think
we're in uncharted territory in most of
these fields you know and that's that's
important to realize you know it's part
of the broader global transformation as
a global transformation the way
knowledge is produced and it means
supervening on the traditional research
academy and blurring those boundaries
they have to be systems biology I mean
they just you name any field and it's to
feelings any relevant fields to fields
you know mind brain and education this
was Kurt Fisher founded the mind brain
and education Society and I worked on
that journal this is a radically
transdisciplinary field so I think yeah
we're it's it's an interesting period to
be someone who has an expertise so I
have training develop but I'm working in
all kinds of fields because the
traditional and a model of what the
developmental psychologist does has
changed so radically and that's that's
the story for a lot of people so I think
we're thinking and people feel it
whether they're supplementing their
graduate education with other gonna
quote non-traditional forms of exposure
you know which are kind of leavening
that and bringing yeah I guess I think I
think going gets weird the weird turn
pearl and that's exactly which it's got
the weird turning pro as opposed to what
was all previously right so now our best
chess players can be beaten by AI our
best go players can be and we that
exponential curve hasn't even barely
started to take off right so when it
comes to health planning we're going to
build tools that would help climb us in
there on every hill right in terms of
excellence what it used to mean of
machines that can outfit a violin or
whatever those in does weight and yet it
is less clear as far as AGI goes if we
would get valley crossing in the same
way at least right now right so then the
hypothesis that education should be more
oriented towards problem finding than
problem solving and then figuring out
how to
nice technology for problem-solving you
say that's a big part of Education yeah
I mean that's a discipline of the
process it's one of the premises of my
book that's coming out soon is that
artificial intelligence and things like
basic income guarantees and radical
changes in the kind of macroeconomic
structure or globally they're gonna make
education as we've known a pretty
irrelevant and we're gonna have to
radically think you know rethink a lot
of things and so the thought of that
problem finding is actually a thought
about values that's what's so
interesting about that and so again the
basic issue in the faucet of Education
is what is a good life what does it mean
to be a good person or to have a good
society and so problem finding is it is
along that trajectory of value and yeah
and that's again we're back to the
humanities and we're back to you yeah
resist the temptation to get into ethics
and existentialism and can you get into
forecasts about exponential tech and
what that means for education and what
the future of education should be flag
those are all podcasts I would like to
do together
coming back to people who are listening
to this that you know there might be
some people who have children are
planning on having children are really
interested in their development
obviously we kind of need to address
that as its own thing but for people who
like a lot of people are coming to neuro
hacker right now because they're
interested in optimizing their own
capacity and their capacity roughly
matches to their cognitive intelligence
capacity it also has to do with will and
drive and creativity and a lot of other
things but so for people who are
thinking about their own capacity and
how they can think about it how they can
support it how they can enhance it you
obviously said that the way of thinking
about intelligence that is roughly valid
in IQ is thinking about the capacity to
develop skills more than a particular
skill except of course the pool shitty
narrative was that's genetically fixed
and then just kind of goes
with age as your brain declines as
opposed to every time you get a skill
that becomes now the knowledge there
actually becomes a model for learning
more stuff so you can actually have an
exponential rate of growth where all the
skills and all the knowledge you develop
become a basis for increased capacity
for developing new things if you do
lateral thinking and abstraction and
generalization well right so a question
that I have because you mentioned a
number of things you said if you expose
the kids from poor backgrounds to the
number line that they just might not
have been exposed to they start to do
better if we're thinking about adults
who already have they already did their
SATs their IQ test they have some sense
of kind of fixed capacity there and but
they like to see if it's not fixed if it
is developable one how much what do we
think about innate versus developable in
terms of raw capacity and where there is
relevance or not to that story and then
what do we think about best processes
for developing what we would roughly
call the kind of any of the lens of
intelligence and I would say
particularly the ones that relate to the
it or objective categories totally yes
the first question that's again is one
of this question that comes up with the
IQ testing right which is basically no
is it you know is it a mater can you
change this thing and I think the answer
is yes
all right there's clearly some genetic
it's undeniable that if you take a broad
swath of the population and given my IQ
test it's gonna accurately kind of
represent something and now many of
those people will not change a lot in
terms of if they're any good metatheory
about what that is I saw one study on
genetics that looked at people with
above 170 IQ whole genome assessments
and I think what it said was no
individual snips made they had high
correlation but there were patterns
combinatorial patterns across the whole
genome probably to do something like you
know increased grey matter density or
something you
are there any kind of I don't know and I
think I you know philosophically like
the concept of heritability itself is
complicated right so technically my
hands are I didn't inherit my hands his
heritability has to do with correlations
and and it's on the percent correlation
so so yeah so I'm not sure that we know
enough about genetics you have to really
speculate and so it's hard to know if I
inherited my dad's breaking or if I
inherited my dad's environment and but
it's clear that you know there are
differences and there are things that
are harder to change and things that are
more malleable I think one other reason
we don't know the answer of this
question is because basic levels like
like Maslow level one kind of like
physical kind of nutrition and safe
environments and these things are not
really available for many people on the
planet and so when you get these
sweeping studies about IQ differences
across let's say race or nationality or
these things it's like can't really make
inferences about anything it made or
genetic here because we're looking at
you know he's malnourished and you know
and so the nourishment of the brain
isn't just nutrition it's also the
information and semiotic right
environment and a lack of drama and fear
and right don'tlet and so that's another
reason I'm always so hesitant to say
what to Nate because it's until we start
to get really optimal basic conditions
for people it's really hard it's really
hard to say what was in their genes and
what was became epigenetic from you from
the womb so I think we're looking at
kind of nature of I am nurture as
opposed to nature versus nurture and
when it comes to changing intelligence
of their own intelligence there's
there's so much you know exercising
nutrition number one focus you know a
lot of what an IQ test gets that is just
your ability to sit still and focus like
when they are with the first kind of
1917 army alphas I mean what they were
really getting the I was can this farm
boys sit at a desk and take this test
for 20 minutes that was really the main
tip I'm
what they really captured so the things
that allow you to focus and give
attention are very important so
meditation is classic but even just the
concerted effort to control your own
informational environment focus on one
thing at a time which our culture it's
hard to do so and I put that under
nutrition because that's like as I said
your your your mind is metabolic with
the environment and so I'm very careful
with what I eat even if it's information
so what are the psychic toxins that you
want not to be eating as far as
intelligences that's interesting I think
of them as kind of invasive species and
the ecology of the mind you know I think
advertisement is a great one one of the
reasons that we are driven to
distractions because of the culture the
advertisement that we have you know and
then in general things that shorten the
attention span by design right not
things that's sure in the attention span
because they're naturally short like a
bird flies by okay
but there are things that shorten our
attention span by design and so we need
to avoid those things because they teach
us that that's how information work so
that's how learning is and if someone
goes to a web site where they take an
article and break it up into 20 next
buttons to maximize that good suggests
avoiding those websites or the yeah it's
not so much what is it maybe it's good
article maybe it's or not but literally
the action of doing that is different
from sitting with a book and so I'm
saying you know not it'll engage fully
with the culture but be mindful that you
can have junk food for your mind yeah
you're gonna junk food for your body and
the cult and that's the stuff that the
culture wants us to eat right and so you
have to find the secret hidden good
stuff in the back where it's a long
article with no it's actually
independent of what you're studying just
focusing for a period of time focused in
the muscle of focus whether it's
changing neural structures and the
connectomics of it or whatever it is
right there is some kind of development
of the capacity for focus probably
intensity of focus and duration of focus
right so that's important but then you
could be focused on very different
topics and you might say that some
topics obviously whether the information
is accurate or not and if it's factual
information 10th matters but are there
certain topics that you think have more
relevance or ways of studying them or
ways of thinking about them well this is
where it gets interesting because the
very next thing I was about to say is
that you also need to learn about
learning there is to say one of the most
important things you can focus on is the
nature of development itself and the
nature of your own learning so learn
about the nature of learning
scientifically but also learn about your
own unique learning needs and patterns
right so not everyone can sit with a
book for 45 minutes but they can do 15
minutes get up staring space walk around
15 minutes get up staring space walk
around right so you learn how you work
and a lot of research can help with that
things like the neuro hacker resources
all of these things should be grist for
that mill but one of the things that you
see with people who go postconventional
and can it become self actualized and
move up to these higher levels that
they're very reflective about their own
learning they know how they learn when
they learn best I know what excites them
to know how to follow investigative
patterns independently and so they're
reflective and so they create these
virtuous cycles of learning for
themselves naturally throughout life as
opposed to being kind of extrinsically
motivated and driven which is what the
schools yeah so this is a quantified
self process around it one way to do it
to quantify it totally and that can help
you know you can also mistake the
numbers for reality with the quantified
self - so again it's not numbers are
great if they're measuring something
that's there and that's what am i
concerned with the quantified self is
like do you know the measurement errors
on your tools like how often does it
miss measure your heartbeat how often
did not capture what it says to be
capturing I mean the blood sugar
monitors for example or a segment
another psychometric Co metrological
minutes and it's dangerous
similarly with quantified self devices
right now and because we want to curate
the tools that can help his act so far
the sensitivity and specificity is not
good enough for us to feel that the
biofeedback optimization is actually
optimizing rather than something that's
a consumer devices of course there are
medical grade devices that are very good
but we're not seeing good enough
correlation on many of them yet it's
interesting and that's what measurement
does and you know I think a lot about
measurement in general and one of the
things that does is it we can trick
ourselves and it's a person not knowing
what's going on sure it's because you
actually think you know what's going on
and you don't and that's why Demi
realities can be weird and so I love the
quantified self insofar as it's
reflective and it creates that virtuous
cycle but if you're creating a cycle on
feedback that's not accurate then you
can get off course but someone could
have a qualified self feedback that is
also wrong where's but that is actually
a kind of addictive feel-good rather
than a virtuous cycle and they optimize
so this is why you need layers of
self-reflection yeah well and the same
cycle that drive learning drives
addiction right it's the kind of system
dawson's refrain and love how learning
works you need to actually kind of co-op
that kind of yeah opioid cycle into the
dopey yeah dopamine opiates I go into
these learning the virtuous cycles as
opposed to and other things like for
example video game a research and design
they figured out how to capture really
well and it's about that zone of
proximal development or the quotient
Goldilocks zone which is that zone
that's not too hard but not too easy and
so if you know about your own learning
you can put yourself in that situation
all the time where you are not in over
your head and challenge to the point of
giving up but not it's easy to explored
and so you're not learning that's with
that again just an example of what's
being reflected by John learning and
give you the ability to stay in that
zone of proximal development with most
of us on all of your tasks in case you
hear your thought on something there are
a few kind of neural hacking methods
that have some early indicators that
they elevate IQ using that shitty old
metric for whatever it's worth so there
is a neurofeedback study
that showed multiple point increase in a
week of a particular form of medical
neurofeedback there was statistically
significant in adults where that
supposedly doesn't change there is a
there's a technology that website called
zing up and it's basically sensory motor
coordination activities that supposedly
drive neurogenesis and where I should
increase hippocampal volume because
you're actually increasing development
and progenitor neurons and it also
should develop elevation of IQ amongst
other meaningful scores it makes sense
right there's a plausibility that
neurofeedback if you're actually taking
signal from the brain feeding back to
the brains the brain gets a whole new
sensory bandwidths that it didn't have
to refine its own process so you get
increased signal-to-noise of process
within the organ of computation itself
at least one of the organs of
computation that that could increase its
efficiency of process independent of
information content information input
right just process information input it
makes sense that if you're increasing
neurogenesis and you're getting actual
gray matter density increases you could
increase the you know the computational
Bandits of the system what do you think
of these kinds of things and are there
things that you that you know of that
you think are meaningful intelligence
developing capacities that are kind of
physiologically oriented that's a great
so I love biofeedback I think you know I
think many forms of let's say mental
distress extreme states of consciousness
you know the things that people seek
psychopharmacology for typically from a
psychiatrist these are these are issues
with the brain often physiological
issues now that means we need to treat
them somehow by working on the brain I
don't think that means we need to
intervene necessarily some drastic
chemical way I think there are ways to
do it that are like you're saying brain
and train them that are not let's say
cognitive behavioral therapy but much
more like letting the brain kind of
perceive itself as it were and work in
that way
I think the way you describe how
probable it works is probably correct
now we have to remember of course that
they're moving IQ tests we're not
necessarily living IQ and so I think we
need to have the quality on on the
inside of that quanta which is to say
what does it feel like after going
through those types of biofeedback
techniques do you feel more capacitated
more lucid and insightful for example
and that's I think that the proof is in
that pudding and also with things like
predictive validity but I think these
are the most promising for me of these
forms of biofeedback you know I think
the brain and the body shouldn't be
separated at all and I think one of the
limits to contemporary neuroscience is
that separation so you know the forms of
somatic practice that get people to
inhabit their bodies more I think have a
lot of potential things like you know
the spatial dynamics and yoga and Tai
Chi you know which bring the brain back
into the body and not out of it into
some to just feedback and they don't
know so I think one of the issues we
have and one of the reasons were seeing
kind of an epidemic of I think cognitive
underperformance let's put it that way a
really nice way is the fact that you
know people's bodies themselves are
hurting before it ever becomes kind of a
neurological thing so that's will be
some general advices health mechanistic
for a minute right if someone's body is
actually hurting right they have
physical pain because of their bad
computer organ ominous then we know that
pain is mediated via chemistry and nerve
signals so you're gonna be having
continuous noise input into the nervous
system you're gonna have inflammatory
chemicals inflammatory cytokines it can
cross the blood-brain barrier because
marrow inflammation and affect all
aspects of talk-down neurologic function
including cognitive so getting out of
pain is a way to actually take a load
off the nervous system increasing its
capacity and bandwidth to deal with
other stuff so that's much clearer way
of what I was trying to say that's
exactly what I meant by saying that you
know the you
please but we can think of a lot of
mechanisms right so there are there's a
lot of studies going on regarding
epigenetics genetic expression from
various forms of exercise and aerobics
versus an aerobics versus high-intensity
interval training actually effects
different gene expressions and there's
something like 7,000 genes that we've
identified actually have epigenetic
modulation with different forms of
exercise so that means that whatever we
thought was it may be genetically
attributable as an eight is also not fix
it right it's changeable and it might so
the your yoga might be affecting some of
those things through the breath through
the parasympathetic processes that are
happening from the slow movement and the
proprioception right from the kind of
vagal stimulation that might happen we
might also see though that there's
certain kinds of benefits that high
intensity interval training does to
increasing right like the good stress on
the system that leads to up oblation let
me set a capacity the yoga doesn't right
so you've but like I'm gonna make a
distinction between things that increase
capacity where the capacity was already
decreased from baseline because of
pathology right pane is pathology versus
someone is already in pretty good health
there's no obvious pathology and now
we're wanting to increase baseline so
I'm curious as you as you forecast into
the future and you think about some of
the developmental possibilities there's
obviously like pretty wild future tech
scenarios that are actually getting not
that far out right like brain brain chip
implants are becoming something that is
a lot of companies are investing pretty
heavily and where you would just augment
your processing capacity with the
processing capacity of the entire cloud
running on quantum computers outside of
that right let's assume that we don't
get that ever or anytime soon and we're
looking at increasing endogenous
processing capacity of this system what
do you foresee if if things
well in terms of us being able to have
decreased stress better medical systems
better schooling education psychological
development what do you see in terms of
then not-too-distant future human
intelligence as what would the general
capacity look like and what might some
of the modalities that we starting aging
will look like right right I said I mean
yeah so the kind of concrete utopian
vision of the future of intelligence you
know would be one where the broad
baseline is raised in a huge way right
so we have a basic income guarantee and
kind of an integral social safety net
and some of these other social miracles
that I've written about we would look at
something like a broad kind of grazing
of the floor of what called general
intelligence just because so much as a
result of that you know but I think for
the individuals looking at the cutting
edge you know I think it's about
horizontal and vertical growth in a
simplistic way that's kind of stereotype
but we don't know the range of people's
multiple intelligences which is to say
the first step for many people is just
to explore lines that they have not
explored right so it's not they keep
going up we can talk about that it's
about going going wider right and it's
we already discussed this briefly but
that I think is something that people
will have the freedom to do in a way
they've never had before if some of
these other things get sorted out why do
they intentionally cross applying yeah
give the intentional crossing of line in
a space not a scarcity where you're
frantically trying to keep your job and
how could I possibly take up yoga right
but in a space of educational abundance
where your unique skull you like the
unique skill profile that you have as a
potential could actually be expressed I
think what we're looking at now are kind
of truncated skill profiles where a lot
of potentials are not expressed for a
variety of reasons so I think the first
issue is to kind of fill that out which
is to say to fill out the rest of your
kind of profile of what you're kind of
capable of doing and that may mean you
work in hospice care or it may mean
working soup kitchen maybe playing
soccer right I mean who knows but the
point being that you know we're limited
in the ways we can grow often by this
sense of educational scarcity that
surrounds us is limits of time so you
know I'll have no problem
go for it expand horizontally I think
another thing again this is about the
unexplored kind of educational frontier
right another place where we haven't
explored as States right so do a lot of
learning and skill development but state
experiences which is the same meditative
States right and other forms of flow
which is another state that's very
popular these days to speak about you
know these the exploration of state
experiences and the way these interface
with capacity development I think it's
another place for people to if they're
topped out at a certain capacity let's
say start to bring in a state practice
which brings that capacity to operate
under a different state and then you'll
find new potential emergence all right
and there's another thing that our
schooling at society doesn't give us
explicitly but that we're seeking on the
side all the time I mean sometimes
explicitly been meditation but rock
concerts movies all of these things are
subtle state inducing causal state
losing so I think there's a way that
when we're not as concerned with
manipulating and kind of you know
competing and when there's a sense of
educational abundance then the value of
those state experiences aesthetic
experience as a state experience and the
rapture of a sunset is a state
experience like the value and the
intrinsic value of those things will
become clearer and clearer and clearer
and it's hard you have to searching for
those now and I think that but I just
want to reiterate in slightly different
words which is that much of how we've
been developing ourselves as like
monoculture in our mind right like we're
trying to produce this thing so we are
just growing hybridized GM wheat fields
and
and not developing a robust complex
ecosystem that can actually resist
foreign species when they come in and
has resilience across a lot of different
capacity so one of the things that
you're wanting is that people don't keep
trying to just optimize the total amount
of wheat yield of their mind but they're
actually seeking to optimize a lot more
complex set of things well you wouldn't
even really call it optimized and you
would call it exploring yeah and that's
I think good for a few reasons you know
one is that the world we're moving into
is not a world where monocultures are
gonna survive on multiple levels and an
analogy so apt because the monoculture
of Agriculture came around the same time
that we got these mass you know kind of
post or high schools and so you're
looking at literally the generation of a
monoculture of the mind
so that's deep and so yeah so it's about
breaking out of that monoculture into
this much more kind of symbiotic way of
thinking about where is my niche and has
a niche can change as the culture around
me changes as I grow and grow more and
so it's very much moving away from the
static kind of almost arithmetic 'el
like like in a sense of arithmetic way
of thinking about the mind into a
dynamical way of thinking about the mind
so yeah so that's that's a good good
insight and so it's about exploration
but it's an exploration the hope of
finding which is to say that you
searcher than you find them and also and
something grows that never would have
grown which may be exactly what's needed
and that's I think the fear of the
monocultures that's not resilient
there's all these reasons that's
literally dangerous so if you can only
do one thing if you can only give one
food to the world and or only eat one
kind of food from the world then you're
very in a precarious situation so we
need to all become very much you know
very broad and I think the Renaissance
man it's like necessary for everybody so
I agree we this and there's an
interesting question I wanna bring up I
have two friends where I've had this
conversation in the last few weeks who
have something like six standard
deviations more computational processing
power than most people off of normal
assessment curves they also have other
underdeveloped capacities as a result of
how they've developed that and a both
expressed fear in doing things that
would develop those other capacities
because if not wanting to lose the
unique capacities that they've developed
or there's a question of like have I
have I allocated all of my neural
process in some zero sum or even if it's
positive some fixed you know positive
some kind of way where I am now a very
useful tool and if I were to reallocate
it it might make me feel better but I
would actually be a less useful tool Zhi
Hao founded do you think that kind of
concern in those outlier cases is I mean
I think again these are deep questions
in the philosophy of education which is
about what's a good person what's a good
society and I think you don't want to
put a square peg in a round hole so
there's that there's a uniqueness factor
and there's a kind of where does the
puzzle piece fit factor but there's
something true also about that fear I
this is kind of a far transfer of the
word but I remember David Lynch ride the
great film director he went to do
psychotherapy and he was like you know
if I do this you know well my art suffer
and the therapist was like maybe you
know and he was like nope not done and
so he was willing to like live with the
wound to do the art and so I think some
people may be willing to live with a
kind of truncated a whole set of skills
and kind of withered limb as it were in
order to have this super strong branch
over here holding up something that
needs to be held up so I think there's a
nod we don't want our modulus you know
but the question is then about what does
it feel like to be them and there are
other things that if they could change
them and not lose that they would and so
I'd have a conversation that would but
that's a deep question and I think we're
looking at a society of increasing
neurodiversity
an increasing kind of unique individual
niche fitting and so we need to be
careful and judicious about trying to
fit square pegs and around all
and trying to maybe perhaps make new
shapes you know fit the shape more to
this unique neural profile then to what
you know the machine needs and again the
machine is that arithmetic mentality the
machine whereas the dynamical mentality
is one where there's a kind of co-active
system between both so yeah this is
again educational futures for those who
don't have the language machine is a
complicated system right eco system is a
complex system ecosystem is changing it
as no fixed blueprint cannot predict its
future stage from the current state
perfectly and it's self-organizing in
response to its environment complicated
system might have a lot that goes into
the circuit design to the blueprinting
of it and but once it does it's fixed it
is not self repairing not
self-organizing and not adaptive humans
understand complicated systems we build
them all we understand much better than
complex systems we're just starting to
understand complex systems so you're
thinking about the mind is a complex
system which is of course makes sense
because the brain is a complex system
the physiology complex system eco system
is right culture that's informing the
mind is a complex system and that one of
the things that it sounds like you're
saying is that we've been using
complicated system metaphors how do we
make it a better machine a better
computer a better robot a better you
know Turing machine whatever right for
something that is actually a complex
dynamic which means supported in
fundamentally different ways and you
optimize complicated systems you support
the emergence of complex systems so
rather than thinking about reductionist
metric optimization of a complicated
mind we think about what supports the
flourishing of self development and auto
police's of a complex mind right
beautiful
yeah and that's again that's both of the
kind of brilliance of the IQ and the
tragedy is that it's simplified this
incredibly complex thing to a single
number which had something you know was
useful there's also dangerous but but
you have the mind is not like that it's
not complicated it's radically complex I
it's literally the most complex thing in
the universe aside from the universe
itself Rises this is the brain and so
the inside of the brain is that now
again start to do some state practices
and you'll see that there's there's some
of that so it's just very interesting to
think about what that future of the
brain in education is you said one thing
that was so important which was you know
like complicated versus complex that's
one big distinction but one of the other
distinctions was intrinsic versus
extrinsic value and most the time when
we think about developing our
intelligence we're thinking about how we
can be a better tool either so that we
can crush the competition or make more
money or right you know raised in some
corporate ladder like be better at some
tasks that we can be externally perfect
and that might be just because of
wounded childhood ego that didn't kill
enough from them being smart was our
compensation strategy so we get to be
enough and you know like it and you're
asking this question of while developing
our extrinsically recognizable and
valuable qualities what is the intrinsic
quality of experience of how we are
developing and just experiencing life
moment moment and obviously for an
educational system valuing the child's
intrinsic experience as well as
developing their capacities for
extrinsic utility but not mostly just
seeing them as utilities for the future
of economy or military or whatever but
then also for all of us as adults we're
paying more attention to balance just to
cram yeah absolutely I think we're you
know extrinsic motivation is part of
what it means to be alive you know I
mean there's always going to be
extrinsic motivations but if that's all
you have it can become very difficult
and it's a classic principle and yeah
psychotherapy if you're totally
dependent upon the world
you know you're very vulnerable it's a
very precarious situation and it feels
that way when you're trapped in a
situation of time to extract a value so
freeing your goals from that
transcending but including extrinsic
value right which is the site you get
that and then you move beyond it and you
include the kind of getting the
extrinsic scale you
include that within this broader project
that's intrinsic and similar to that
transfer thing we discussed before
bringing it all together into a kind of
coherence of development of self so in
an interesting part you know that's part
of it you know again as I said the
people who become post conventional you
find them to be self-directed learners
and intrinsically motivated and even
those who are a great example of this is
dyslexia right i'm dyslexic it's it's
actually true that dyslexic you know who
succeed
the reason they succeed is not because
of the special training they received
it's because they attach an intrinsic
motivation to something like reading and
so you find all these stories of you
know high achievement dyslexics and at
some point in their childhood they found
something they were just passionate
about and so all the pain of school and
all of that didn't matter anymore
because their intrinsic an little bit at
a low and by the way along the way they
got these extrinsic things handled but
they're doing them for their own reasons
and so there's something I think many of
the people who are the valley crossers
end up being mavericks and outsiders in
traditional schooling precisely for this
reason because they're doing it for
their own purposes they're intrinsically
motivated and the school demands certain
extremes of things so that kind of
separation of learning from schooling
often follows from the separation of
intrinsic from extreme lack and that's
the advice I give to most of my friends
who have kids and like accessory and
learning from schooling learning is
awesome schooling sometimes can be
sometimes not it's a watch but if you
confuse those and think learning so it
takes place in school yeah then you'll
never learn for the rest your life and
so that intrinsic motivation is huge and
but that it's really deep really quickly
that's the problem with intrinsic
motivations and you go directly from you
know simple questions about what am i
learning too deep questions about what's
the significance of my life what do I
really want to be what kind of person am
I already what can I transform like
these are the deeper questions
which the degree that we are wanting to
raise children to fill roles and a
predefined society we of course don't
want them to ask right that's what they
have to ask okay this has been a blast
as we're wrapping up if people are
interested in understanding their
capacities as a baseline to both see
what is most relevant for them to
develop and then to see if the
developmental things they're doing are
working other than IQ what might you
recommend to people as ways they can
assess their intelligence their multiple
lines of intelligence their ecological
complexity of thought like what is
electrically useful tool what are some
other ones for assessment yeah electic
a-- so you can go to luck to go dot org
and i'm sure there'll be links on the
neuro hacker website that we can put
there and there's a there's a few
assessment options I like to go which
they get it that spectrum from
abstraction and complexity in particular
lines and these can be useful for self
diagnostic purposes there's a whole
bunch of uses for electrical assessments
so I think those are important addition
again it's about the standardization and
the psychometric over their valuable
whose array of assessments out there
which you could use in a quantified self
type way and so I would never discourage
people from exploring those but I think
you know keep in mind all these lessons
about measurement and measurement of the
mind in particular and just take them
with a grain of salt you know and know
that you know flying blind
which is to say without measures is
better than flying with measures your
trusts that are wrong and that's that's
just true and so play with them but
really be careful about the ones you
hang your hat on and you know journaling
there's actually extremely important
developmental catalyst so which is to
say witness at all note at all seasons
where you can see what's not working pay
attention to yourself and sometimes
journaling where they can help with that
fundamental way you can do it in a
structured way and there's a whole
approaches to doing that but I found it
to be valuable for people that I know
from my
so that's just another way of assessment
you know you talked about the cap of
quanta and the qualia right and so
that's the qualitative assessment
themself and you can keep it running log
it around head but writing it down helps
gets it out and have you seen any
correlation of things like different
forms of imaging so say MRIs that are
looking at neural density QE G's and
different forms of psychometric or
intelligence scores that you think are
either already valuable or promising of
a new kind of mind brain interface
science I mean this is my room my field
I haven't I mean I've been really
intrigued by the meditation research
that's coming out of Madison Wisconsin I
think that's where it is and that's the
it's interesting because it's an ancient
technology of self development and it's
showing profound neurological as you'd
expect but it's just shocking to see
really how how stark some of these
findings are so that's intriguing to me
but yeah that's about as much as I can
say you know and so I'm kind of
old-school methods I think it's part of
my part of it comes from my caution
around the assessment you know which is
to say I'm you know the DSM is a
nightmare the IQ tests are a nightmare
like don't caps don't articulate your
self understanding in these languages
handed to you you know find new ways to
think about myself
things like Plaxico can help like that
but Nix and wrong metrics are concerned
for you but metrics objective metrics
about subjectivity are their own
category of nightmare right right yeah
and then you get the metrics at work and
then those are scary foreigners because
they actually work and so there's too
many we can just jump down the whole
thing but we need to go this is good
Zack this was a blast thank you there's
a really fun first podcast for us to do
and a fun topic and I imagine people
might have a lot of follow-up questions
regard
during assessment and development and
etc and we might get to follow up on
those so thank you welcome all right
thank you for listening to collective
insights for the full show notes on this
episode and for more great interviews
visit us at neuro hacker.com slash
collective insights if you liked this
episode please subscribe to the podcasts
and leave us a five star review on
iTunes